Okay בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, today's דף Daf is פ"ט, Peh-Tet, 189,
we pick up with the משנה Mishnah at the bottom of פ"ח
עמוד ב', Peh-Chet Amud Bet, about ten lines from the bottom. חומר
בדברי סופרים מדברי תורה: Chomer bedivrei sofrim midivrei Torah: in a way,
things that are not rabbinic, דברי סופרים Divrei Sofrim here means a
rabbinic interpretation of the פסוקים, Psukim, can be weightier than the actual
things that are explicit in the פסוקים. Psukim. האומר אין תפילין כדי
לעבור על דברי תורה פטור: Ha'omer ein tefillin bikdei la'avor al divrei
torah patur: if a זקן ממרא Zaken Mamre were to say there's
no such thing as תפילין, Tefillin, directly going against explicit פסוקים Psukim
in the תורה, Torah, he'd be פטור, Patur, because that's not a
הוראה. Hora'ah. זקן ממרא Zaken Mamre has positioned himself as a פוסק
Posek in defiance of בית דין. Beit Din. Okay, you'd be פטור,
Patur, that's not a הוראה. Hora'ah. חמש טוטפות להוסיף על דברי סופרים
חייב: Chamesh totafot lehosif al divrei sofrim chayav: however, if he says
yes there is תפילין Tefillin in the תורה, Torah, but it's not
four בתים Batim in the של ראש, Shel Rosh, it's five בתים,
Batim, then he is חייב. Chayav. That is a הוראה Hora'ah and
therefore you could be חייב. Chayav. So something that's less explicit, you're
more חייב Chayav for because there's an element of paskening where there
is not in the first case. Let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara. By the way, that makes it clear according to this
משנה, Mishnah, not like רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, that you do not
need something that you are חייב Chayav like that's about כרת Karet
and חטאת Chatat and so on. This is the broader position of
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that anything constitutes a זקן ממרא. Zaken Mamre.
Okay, אמר רבי אלעזר
אמר רבי אושעיא, Amar Rabbi Elazar amar Rabbi Oshaya, אינו חייב אלא
על דבר שעיקרו מדברי תורה ופירושו מדברי סופרים ויש בו להוסיף אם
הוסיף גורע. Eino chayav ela al davar she'ikaro midivrei torah uperusho midivrei
sofrim veyesh bo lehosif im hosif gore'ah. Okay, so he's making it
much
narrower than the משנה. Mishnah. Our משנה Mishnah gave תפילין Tefillin as
an example, but it basically said anything that's not explicit. He is
saying no, the only thing that a זקן ממרא Zaken Mamre is
חייב Chayav for is something that starts with something explicit in the
תורה, Torah, but there's a rabbinic understanding of what the parameters are—okay,
that's still most of תורה, Torah, right? What constitutes שבת, Shabbat, what
constitutes anything, there's always a פירושו מדברי סופרים—ויש בו להוסיף, but here's
where it gets very narrow: what you did is you added something
that wasn't there, אם הוסיף גורע, Im hosif gore'ah, but through adding,
it subtracted. Okay, so in our case of the משנה, Mishnah, he
said there was a fifth בית, Bayit, but because he said there
was a fifth
בית Bayit of compartment of the תפילין, Tefillin, that made the תפילין
Tefillin פסול. Pasul. דאנו אין לנו אלא תפילין: De'anu ein lanu ela
Tefillin: and that only example would be the one case in the
משנה. Mishnah. So before we said we had so many examples of
everything under the sun, we're now going to take the case in
our משנה Mishnah and say that is the only case. And אליבא
דרבי יהודה, Aliba d'Rabbi Yehuda, it's like רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda who
said על פי התורה אשר יורוך, Al pi hatorah asher yoruha, that
it has to be תורה, Torah, something explicit in the פסוקים, Psukim,
and יורוך, Yoruha, there has to be an interpretation. Now again, that
would actually on the face of it be even broader than רבי
מאיר, Rabbi Meir, pretty much anything that there's a תורה שבעל פה
Torah sheba'al peh component to. But he is adding this idea of
מוסיף וגורע Mosif ve'gore'ah and limiting it ממש Mamash just to the
case of תפילין. Tefillin. Okay,
והא איכא לולב? Veha ika Lulav?
But the גמרא Gemara says one minute, what about לולב? Lulav? דעיקרו
מדברי תורה ופירושו מדברי סופרים. De'ikaro midivrei torah uperusho midivrei sofrim. What
are the מינים Minim in a לולב? Lulav? That's also interpretation of
חז"ל. Chazal. ויש בו להוסיף: Veyesh bo lehosif, you could add, if
you added an extra מין, Min, you would be adding to what
the תורה Torah says. אם הוסיף גורע: Im hosif gore'ah: and if
you add, you take off, you invalidate the ארבע מינים. Arba'ah Minim.
So the גמרא Gemara says no. מאי סבירא לך? Mai sevira lach?
What do you assume? אי סבירא לך דלולב אין צריך אגד: Ei
sevira lach deLulav ein tzarich eged: if you assume that the binding
we make with the לולב, Lulav, הדסים, Hadasim, and ערבות Aravot is
not required in the תורה, Torah, so האי לחוד קאי והאי לחוד
קאי: Hai lachud ka'i vehai lachud ka'i: even if you said there
was an additional מין Min that you had to add to the
לולב, Lulav, you would not invalidate the לולב. Lulav. You might be
over on בל תוסף Ba'al Tosif when you took it, if you
took an extra מין—maybe Min yes, maybe no, it's not exactly clear
whether we're talking about the עבירה Aveira of בל תוסף—okay, Ba'al Tosif
maybe you say האי לחוד קאי Hai lachud ka'i and you're not
even being over on בל תוסף, Ba'al Tosif, but even if you
are, because each one stands by itself, you're not redefining the מצווה
Mitzvah object and invalidating it. So it's not מוסיף גורע. Mosif gore'ah.
ואי סבירא לך דצריך אגד: Vei sevira lach detzarich eged: now if
a לולב Lulav needs to be bound, those three מינים, Minim, גרוע
ועומד הוא: Garua ve'omed hu: and you made a thing that included
לולב, Lulav, הדסים, Hadasim, ערבות, Aravot, and I don't know, and a
palm and an oak branch, okay, then that bundle would already be
an invalid bundle. It would be four pieces and not three pieces
and it would inherently be invalid to start with. As opposed to
being כשר Kosher but the addition made it פסול. Pasul. Now you're
going to ask, how's that any different than the תפילין? Tefillin? So
hold on, we will see. Okay, but that never started as being
good and became ungood from the very moment it was bundled, it
was all invalid object.
והא איכא ציצית? Veha ika Tzitzit? What about
ציצית? Tzitzit? דעיקרו מדברי תורה... De'ikaro midivrei torah... If you add an
extra string to your ציצית, tzitzis, right? ואם הוסיף גורע, ve'im hosif
gore'a, and if you do, you would invalidate it. So the גמרא
Gemara would say, one minute, but ציצית tzitzis מאי סבירא ליה? mai
sevira leih? What do you assume? אי סבירא ליה ei sevira leih
דקשר עליון לאו דאורייתא, dekesher elyon lav de'oraisa, if you're assuming that
the top knot is not דאורייתא, de'oraisa, which nobody really assumes, but
even if you were to argue that, האי לחודא קאי והאי לחודא
קאי, hai lechuda kai vehai lechuda kai, if you added an extra
string, okay, it would be standing by itself, it wouldn't invalidate, it
wouldn't redefine the מצוה mitzvah object. ואי סבירא ליה, ve'ei sevira leih,
and if you hold, top of
פ"ט עמוד א, peh tes amud alef, דקשר העליון דאורייתא, dekesher ha'elyon
de'oraisa, the top knot is דאורייתא, de'oraisa, which is how we פסקן,
pasken, גרע ועומד, gara ve'omed, as soon as you made that first
knot you'd have too many strings and it would be invalid. So
it wouldn't be something that would be כשר kosher and then the
addition made it invalid. It never started as כשר. kosher. So the
גמרא Gemara says, אי הכי תפילין נמי. ei hachi tefillin nami. So
the גמרא Gemara says same by תפילין. tefillin. אי עביד ארבעה בתי,
ei avid arba'ah battei, if you started with four בתים battim on
your תפילין, tefillin, ואסחינהו ואנח גבייהו, ve'aschina ve'anach gabeihu, and then you
made a fifth sort of compartment that you then stuck on, you
know, to the תפילין, tefillin, so האי לחודא קאי והאי לחודא קאי,
hai lechuda kai vehai lechuda kai, it's a separate unit and it
doesn't invalidate what you have in your, you know, your unit of
four. Each one stands by itself. דעביד חמישה בתי, de'avid chamishah battei,
and if you created initially a unit of five, גרע ועומד הוא,
gara ve'omed hu, that's just like knotting extra strings in your טלית,
tallis, in your ציצית, tzitzis, or putting extra מינים minim in your
לולב. lulav. You start with something invalid. So how is this any
different? אמר רבי זירא, amar Rebbi Zeira, בית חיצון שאינו רואה את
האויר פסול. bayis chitzon she'eino ro'eh es ha'avir pasul. No, what made
it invalid is not the five per se, but you need the
outer compartments, you know, to be exposed to the air. So when
you added a fifth compartment, even though it's האי לחודא קאי, hai
lechuda kai, so it started כשר, kosher, you had four compartments, you
added a fifth, even though it's האי לחודא קאי, hai lechuda kai,
it doesn't redefine it as a unit of five compartments, it invalidated
it by not making the outer compartment, the outer edge of the
outer compartment exposed to the open air. All right, so that's interesting
but, you know, it's not really at all clear why רבי אלעזר
Rebbi Elazar makes this, you know, very very limited idea that it's
not just needs a rabbinic component and based on a תורה, Torah,
which is what the משנה mishna says, but it actually needs this
מוסיף גורע mosif gore'a and so on, and why that's the definition
of זקן ממרא. zaken mamre. There's actually, you know, no פסוקים pesukim
or whatever are quoted to explain that. Let's take a look at
the next משנה, mishna, continuing with זקן ממרא. zaken mamre. אין ממיתין
אותו לא בבית דין שבעירו ולא בבית דין שביבנה, ein memisin oso
lo beveiyis din shebe'iro velo beveiyis din shebe'Yavneh, you don't execute him
in his local בית דין beis din or in the בית דין
beis din in יבנה. Yavneh. רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafos try to
figure out why are we mentioning the בית דין beis din in
יבנה? Yavneh? The בית דין beis din in יבנה Yavneh really only
came to prominence after there was no longer a בית דין beis
din in the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, and you needed the בית
דין beis din in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash for somebody to
be a זקן ממרא. zaken mamre. But okay, even in a major
בית דין beis din outside of the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, אלא
מעלין אותו לבית דין הגדול
שבירושלים. ella ma'alin oso leveis din hagadol shebeYerushalayim. There's only one place
to do this, his judgment, which is in the בית דין הגדול
שבירושלים. beis din hagadol shebeYerushalayim. We know he has to reject their
ruling, but it's not enough that he reject the ruling of the
בית דין הגדול שבירושלים, beis din hagadol shebeYerushalayim, that's where you have
to have his גמר דין gmar din and that's where you have
to actually execute him. ומשמרין
אותו עד הרגל, umeshamrin oso ad haregel, you wait until it's a
רגל, regel, וממיתין אותו ברגל, umemisin oso baregel, and you execute him
on the רגל, regel, שנאמר, וכל העם ישמעו וייראו she-ne'emar ve-chol ha-am
yishme'u ve-yira'u, ולא יזידון עוד. Everybody has to hear and be afraid.
This is again to protect the authority of the בית דין, beis
din, and that's why you do it on the רגל regel and
in the בית דין הגדול Beis Din HaGadol to emphasize their authority.
דברי רבי עקיבא. divrei Rebbi Akiva. רבי יהודה אומר, Rebbi Yehuda omer,
אין מענין את דינו של זה. ein me'annin es dino shel zeh.
You do not postpone and cause עינוי הדין, innui hadin, a suffering
of the judgment of this person once there was a גמר דין.
gmar din. You do it immediately. You don't wait for the רגל.
regel. Okay, אלא ממיתין אותו מיד. ella memisin oso miyad. Now presumably
it would still be in the בית דין הגדול, Beis Din HaGadol,
not in his local city, because he rebelled against the
בית דין הגדול, Beis Din HaGadol, so you do it immediately, but
you don't wait till the רגל. regel. וכותבין ושולחין שלוחין בכל המקומות,
vekosvin vesholchin sheluchin bechol hamakomos, איש פלוני נתחייב מיתה בבית דין. ish
ploni nis'chayav misa beveiyis din. But and then what do you do
with וכל העם ישמעו וייראו? vechol ha'am yishme'u veyira'u? You send out
messages to everybody but you don't wait for everybody to gather. Okay,
so that's what you do.
Okay, but presumably again, you know, everything would be in the בית
דין הגדול, Beis Din HaGadol,
but now I should say that there's actually a difference between where
he gets executed and where his גמר דין gmar din is. Because
interestingly, even though all of this is challenging the authority of the
בית דין הגדול, Beis Din HaGadol, if you go back to the
very very first משנה mishna of סנהדרין Sanhedrin of the things that
require seventy-one, you will see that it does not say that the
judgment of the זקן ממרא zaken mamre requires a בית דין beis
din of seventy-one, right? So it says, and here it says he
went back to his city and he taught there. So actually רמב"ם
Rambam makes this explicit and רמב"ם Rambam actually says that the בית
דין beis din in his city will judge him as a זקן
ממרא, zaken mamre, but then from there he gets brought to ירושלים.
Yerushalayim. where actually he is executed, and that's the language of מעלין
אותו לבית דין הגדול Ma'alin oto le-Beit Din ha-Gadol in our משנה.
Mishna. So when רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says אין מענין ein ma'anin
את דינו של זה, et dino shel zeh,
so if his judgment was actually in, what do you call it,
in his local בית דין, Beit Din, then they would be executed
in his local בית דין. Beit Din. So I think I might
have said that a little bit incorrectly before. But anyway, but so
the question is he would be judged in his local בית דין,
Beit Din, he'd go back locally, and then the question is now
where do you execute him? תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says it would
be in the בית דין הגדול Beit Din ha-Gadol and רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda presumably would be in his local בית דין, Beit Din,
but you would send out the messages everywhere. Okay, בכל מקום וכותבין
ושולחין בכל מקום איש פלוני נתחייב מיתה בבית דין. Be-chol makom ve-chotvin
ve-sholchin be-chol makom ish ploni nitchayav mita be-veit din. By the way,
I should also say mentioning רמב"ם Rambam that רמב"ם, Rambam, you know,
deals with the whole idea of this משנה Mishna about לולב, lulav,
you know, and this discussion in the גמרא Gemara as an add-on.
He says, of course everything we said before that could lead to
חייב כרת chayav kares and חייב חטאת chayav chatas or whatever, that
would all be זקן ממרא. Zaken Mamre. But if you have something
that's not חייב כרת chayav kares and not חייב חטאת chayav chatas
but fits these parameters here about מוסיף גורע, mosif gore'a, then you're
also זקן ממרא Zaken Mamre for that. So it's like a single
add-on. Okay, anyway let's take a look at the גמרא Gemara now
on דף ט'. daf tet. תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, the rabbis taught,
אין ממיתין אותו לא בבית דין שבעירו ולא בבית דין שביבנה. Ein
memitin oto lo be-veit din she-be-iro ve-lo be-veit din she-bi-Yavne. You don't
execute him in his local בית דין Beit Din and not the
one in יבנה, Yavne, אלא מעלין אותו לבית דין הגדול שבירושלים ומשמרין
אותו עד הרגל וממיתין אותו ברגל, ela ma'alin oto le-Beit Din ha-Gadol
she-bi-Yerushalayim u-mishmrin oto ad ha-regel u-memitin oto ba-regel, שנאמר shene'emar, וכל העם
ישמעו וייראו, yishme'u ve-yira'u, דברי רבי עקיבא. divrei Rabbi Akiva.
Okay, pretty much exactly our משנה. Mishna. You wait till the רגל
regel and you do it there. אמר לו רבי יהודה, Amar lo
Rabbi Yehuda, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said to him, וכי נאמר יראו
וייראו? Ve-chi ne'emar yir'u ve-yira'u? Does it say that everybody will see
and fear, that everybody has to know about it through directly witnessing
it? והלא לא נאמר אלא ישמעו וייראו. Ve-halo lo ne'emar ela yishme'u
ve-yira'u. They'll hear about it and fear. למה מענין את דינו של
זה? Lama ma'anin et dino shel zeh? So why would you, you
know, delay his judgment? אלא ממיתין אותו מיד. Ela memitin oto mi-yad.
You execute him immediately. And as we just discussed, that would mean
that you would do it even in, you would do it in
his local בית דין Beit Din where he was judged, וכותבין ושולחין
בכל מקום איש פלוני נתחייב מיתה בבית דין. ve-chotvin ve-sholchin be-chol makom
ish ploni nitchayav mita be-veit din. And then you would just get,
send the messages out. Okay, תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, the rabbis taught,
ארבעה צריכים הכרזה, Arba'ah tzerichin hachrazah, four people you have to announce
throughout the land of Israel that they were executed because it says
explicitly in the פסוק, pasuk, וכל ישראל ישמעו וייראו. ve-chol Yisrael yishme'u
ve-yira'u. Okay,
המסית, ha-meisit, the one who seduces to עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, ובן
סורר ומורה, u-ben sorer u-moreh, the בן סורר ומורה, ben sorer u-moreh,
וזקן ממרא, ve-zaken mamre, and עדים זוממים. edim zomemin. All of them
it says וכל ישראל ישמעו וייראו. ve-chol Yisrael yishme'u ve-yira'u. בכולהו כתיב,
Be-chulhu ketiv, as the גמרא Gemara says, בהו וכל העם או וכל
ישראל. behu ve-chol ha-am o ve-chol Yisrael. ובעדים זוממים, u-ve-edim zomemin, the
one exception with עדים זוממים, edim zomemin, כתיב והנשארים ישמעו וייראו, ketiv
ve-ha-nish'arim yishme'u ve-yira'u, the remainder will ישמעו וייראו, yishme'u ve-yira'u, דלא כל
עמא חזו לסהדותא. de-la kol amma chazu le-sahaduta. It's not everybody because
not everyone can be an עד. ed. So only the people who
are really taking heart are the people like who are כשר kasher
to be עדים, edim, starting with the men and, you know, and
whatever and not
גזלנים gazlanim etc., etc. Now of course not everybody can be a
בן סורר ומורה ben sorer u-moreh either, but at least it means
that, you know, people will be afraid of parental authority. So רמב"ן
Ramban points out by the way that in all of these cases
what's happening, this is רמב"ן על התורה, Ramban al ha-Torah, what's happening
are is that various institutions are being protected and even the people
are being executed even though the sin itself might not be deserving
of execution, they're they're being executed to protect these institutions. And that's
why it says וכל ישראל ישמעו וייראו. ve-chol Yisrael yishme'u ve-yira'u. So
the most obvious here, two of the things that we often say,
hey wait, what did they really do? בן סורר ומורה, Ben sorer
u-moreh, which is protecting parental authority, and עדים זוממים, edim zomemin,
which
is protecting the integrity of the courts. So by עדים זוממים, edim
zomemin, you know, the guy didn't actually get executed and they're getting
executed, but again that's וכל ישראל ישמעו וייראו. ve-chol Yisrael yishme'u ve-yira'u.
We have to protect the integrity. זקן ממרא Zaken Mamre is the
authority also of like, you know, the deciding role of the courts,
not the adjudicating, but, you know, their authority to interpret,
and המסית, ha-meisit, of course, you know, God's authority, even if somebody
doesn't listen and nobody is עובד עבודה זרה, oved avodah zarah, they're
undermining the divine authority. And that's why it says ישמעו וייראו, but
that's also why the punishment can be a little disproportionate to the
actual sin. Okay, let's take a look now at the next משנה.
Mishna. נביא השקר, Navi ha-sheker, now we're moving on from זקן ממרא,
Zaken Mamre, the next person of חנק chenek is נביא השקר. navi
ha-sheker. נביא השקר המתנבא מה שלא שמע, Navi ha-sheker ha-mitnabei mah she-lo
shama, somebody who to gives, prophesies something that they never heard, never
got any prophecy about, או מה שלא נאמר לו, o mah she-lo
ne'emar lo, or something that was a prophecy given to his colleagues,
a different נביא, navi, and somehow he found out about it and
then he went around claiming that he had received that prophecy. Now
technically that is also in the category of מה שלא שמע mah
she-lo shama because he did not get that direct prophecy. But nevertheless,
we're saying even though it was a prophecy that was given to
his friend, he's still חייב. chayav. Okay, and that's basically the פסוק,
pasuk, אך הנביא אשר יזיד לדבר דבר בשמי את אשר לא צויתיו
לדבר. ach ha-navi asher yazid ledaber davar bishmi et asher lo tzivitiv
ledaber. ואשר ידבר בשם אלוהים אחרים, va'asher yedaber b'sheim elohim acheirim, something
I did not command and who speaks in the name of other
gods. So that's the next one. So, המנבא מה שלא שמע, hamenabei
masha lo shama, מה שלא נאמר לו, masha lo ne'emar lo, מיתתו
בידי אדם. mitato b'yadei adam. That is somebody that will be killed
through human agency, right?
ומת הנביא ההוא. umeis hanavi hahu. אבל הכובש נבואתו, aval hakoveish nevuato,
somebody that suppresses his his נבואה nevuah and he has he received
a prophecy from God, but he is not going ahead and sharing
it. והמוותר על דברי נביא, v'hamivater al divrei navi, or somebody who
violates the word of a נביא, navi, ונביא שעבר על דברי עצמו,
v'navi she'avar al divrei atzmo, or he violated his own prophecy, okay,
מיתתו בידי שמיים, mitato b'yadei shamayim, that's left to God. שנאמר: shenemar:
אנוכי אדרוש מעמו. anochi edrosh me'imo. Okay, what the פסוק pasuk says:
אשר לא ישמע אל דבריי. asher lo yishma el devarai. Okay, it's
somebody who does not listen to the words, I, God, will take
care of him. So we'll see in the גמרא, Gemara, it's not
somebody who doesn't listen to the words of the נביא, navi, or
אשר לא ישמיע, asher lo yashmiya, does not make them heard, the
נביא navi who does not express them. Right, that's up to God.
המנבא בשם עבודת כוכבים. hamenabei b'sheim avodat kochavim. Now let's say somebody
testifies in the name of עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, right? ואשר ידבר
בשם אלוהים אחרים, va'asher yedaber b'sheim elohim acheirim, also in the פסוק.
pasuk. לומר כך אמר עבודת כוכבים, lomar kach amar avodat kochavim, this
is what this god said. אפילו כיוון את ההלכה, afilu kivein et
hahalachah, לטמא את הטמא ולטהר את הטהור, letamei et hatamei uletahair et
hatahor, even if he's saying this god said that you have to
keep שבת Shabbat and here are the thirty-nine מלאכות melachot etc., and
this is what the, you know, בעל Ba'al told me to tell
all of you to do,
nevertheless, that is a case of a of a נביא שקר. navi
sheker. Alright, now again, it's really still all of the category of
giving a נבואה nevuah that you did not hear from God. Okay,
but nevertheless, it's explained in the פסוק pasuk as a different category.
Now, הבא על אשת איש, haba al eishet ish, now we're totally
moving on, the final category or the penultimate category here of חנק
chenek is somebody who has intercourse with a married woman, adultery.
כיוון שנכנסה לרשות הבעל לנישואין, keivan shenichnesah lirshut haba'al lenisu'in, once she
has gone under the into the husband's domain for the purpose of
חופה, chuppah, אף על פי שלא נבעלה, af al pi shelo niv'alah,
even though she has not yet had sex, but once she's a
נשואה, nesu'ah,
then הבא עליה הרי זה בחנק. haba aleha harei zeh b'chenek. Then
that makes her a married woman who is נשואה nesu'ah and the
and the punishment is חנק. chenek. בת
כהן וזוממי בת כהן ובועלה. bat kohen v'zomemei bat kohen uvo'alah. Now
a בת כהן bat kohen gets שריפה. sreifah. But it's remember: היא
באש תישרף, hi ba'eish tisareif, היא ולא בועלה. hi v'lo vo'alah. Her
husband only gets חנק, chenek, only, whatever. But that's because for him,
it's still not her husband, excuse me, the the person she had
the affair with. Okay, it's adultery, so he gets the standard punishment
of adultery, חנק, chenek, but only she gets שריפה. sreifah. So so
not only that, if people were found to be עדים זוממים eidim
zomemim and trying to be מחייב mechayev her שריפה sreifah because they
are men and she's a woman, they would get the punishment that
the that the lover would get, the adulterer would get, they get
חנק, chenek, not שריפה. sreifah. זוממי בת כהן ובועלה, zomemei bat kohen
uvo'alah, so the one so the one who had sex with the
בת כהן bat kohen or the one עדים זוממים, eidim zomemim, they
also get חנק chenek and not שריפה, sreifah, but ultimately that boils
down to the case of adultery. שכל המוזממין מקדימין לו זו מיתה,
shekol hamuzmamin makdimin lo zo mitah, anybody who's עדים זוממים, eidim zomemim,
they get right away get the מיתה mitah that they were trying
to bring upon the other person. חוץ מזוממי בת כהן ובועלה, chutz
mizomemei bat kohen uvo'alah, the one exception is זוממי בת כהן zomemei
bat kohen because it says היא באש תישרף, hi ba'eish tisareif, only
she gets שריפה, sreifah, all the men involved in this would get
חנק. chenek. Let's see the גמרא. Gemara. תנו רבנן: tanu rabbanan: שלושה
מיתתם בידי אדם ושלושה מיתתם בידי שמיים, shlosha mitatam b'yadei adam ushlosha
mitatam b'yadei shamayim, three cases of the נביא navi get it from
by human agency, three by through God.
המנבא מה שלא שמע, hamenabei masha lo shama, somebody gives נבואה nevuah
from what he did not hear from God. ומה שלא נאמר לו,
umasha lo ne'emar lo, or was given to another נביא navi but
not given to him. והמנבא בשם עבודת כוכבים, v'hamenabei b'sheim avodat kochavim,
or in the name of עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. מיתתם בידי אדם,
mitatam b'yadei adam, they get punished by human agency. הכובש נבואתו והמוותר
על דברי נביא ונביא שעבר על דברי עצמו מיתתם בידי שמיים. hakoveish
nevuato v'hamivater al divrei navi v'navi she'avar al divrei atzmo mitatam b'yadei
shamayim. Okay, that's basically our משנה. Mishnah. מנא הני מילי, mana hanei
milei, where do we know this from? אמר רב יהודה אמר רב
דאמר קרא, amar rav yehudah amar rav de'amar kra, the פסוק pasuk
says: אך הנביא אשר יזיד לדבר דבר בשמי, ach hanavi asher yazid
lidaber davar bishmi, somebody who speaks in my name and then says:
את אשר לא ציוויתיו לדבר, et asher lo tzivitiv lidaber, what I
did not command. זה מתנבא מה שלא שמע. zeh mitnabei masha lo
shama. Okay, that he's doing it on his own, what he didn't
hear. ואשר לא ציוויתיו, va'asher lo tzivitiv, and that I did not
command him to speak, לחברו ציוויתיו, lachaveiro tzivitiv, even if I commanded
his friend to speak it, since he wasn't commanded, that still makes
him a נביא שקר navi sheker because he's saying that he was
given that נבואה. nevuah. Okay, זה מתנבא מה שלא נאמר לו, zeh
mitnabei masha lo ne'emar lo, something that was said not said to
him. ואשר ידבר בשם אלוהים אחרים, va'asher yedaber b'sheim elohim acheirim, זה
מתנבא בשם עבודת כוכבים. zeh mitnabei b'sheim avodat kochavim. Okay, or in
the name of other gods. וכתיב ומת הנביא ההוא, uchetiv umeis hanavi
hahu, he will be put to death. וכל מיתה אמורה בתורה סתם
אינה אלא חנק, vechol mitah amurah batorah stam einah ela chenek, and
סתם מיתה stam mitah is by
strangulation. הכובש נבואתו והמוותר על דברי נביא, hakoveish nevuato v'hamivater al divrei
navi, if
somebody suppresses his נבואה nevuah or violates the word of a
נביא, navi, ונביא שעבר על דברי עצמו. v'navi she'avar al divrei atzmo.
Anyway, the man who does not hear וקרי ביה לא ישמיע, vekaari
beih lo yashmia, read it "does not make heard", so he does
not, he does not go out and preach my words. וקרי ביה
לא ישמע, Vekaari beih lo yishma, "does not hear", he himself does
not obey ישמע
אל דברי, yishma el devarai, וכתיב vechtiv אנכי אדרש מעמו, anochi edrosh
meimo, I will seek it out בידי שמים. biyedei shamayim. So if
you suppress your own נבואה nevuah or you violate or somebody else
violates the נבואה, nevuah, then that is God will take care of
that. Now we're going to go through these individually. המתנבא מה שלא
שמע, Hamitnabe mah shelo shama, somebody who testifies what they did not
hear, כגון צדקיהו בן כנענה, kegon Tzidkiyahu ben Kena'anah, like צדקיהו בן
כנענה, Tzidkiyahu ben Kena'anah, דכתיב ויעש לו צדקיהו בן כנענה קרני ברזל,
dechtiv vaya'as lo Tzidkiyahu ben Kena'anah karnei barzel, and he made these
horns and he said כה תנגח את ארם. koh tinagach et aram.
Okay, but that was because God, a
false spirit told him this testimony. So the Gemara is going to
say מאי
הוה ליה למעבד, mai havah leih leme'evad, but the Gemara asks wait,
he wasn't to blame, you know, he actually received some visitation, some
vision, and that made him believe he had received a prophecy. רוח
נבות אתיא ותיזיל, Ruach Navot ata teizei, the spirit of נבות, Navot,
נבות היזרעאלי Navot Hayizre'eli that was murdered by אחאב, Achav, you know,
his spirit came back to cause this נביא navi to err because
ultimately it was to get אחאב Achav to, as we'll see in
a minute what the פסוקים, pesukim, you know, to fall in battle.
So how can you blame צדקיהו, Tzidkiyahu,
צדקיהו, Tzidkiyahu, you know, he thought he was receiving a נבואה. nevuah.
דכתיב, Dechtiv, now we're going to give the context. ויאמר ה׳ מי
יפתה את אחאב ויעל ויפל ברמת גלעד, Vayomer Hashem mi yefateh et
Achav veya'al veyippol beRamot Gil'ad, who will seduce אחאב, Achav, God said,
who will seduce אחאב Achav and he will go up and he
will fall in רמת גלעד Ramot Gil'ad in battle. ויצא הרוח ויעמד
לפני ה׳, Vayeitzei haruach vaya'amod lifnei Hashem, some spirit came and stood
before God, ויאמר אני אפתנו, vayomer ani afatenu, I will seduce him.
ויאמר תפתה וגם תוכל צא ועשה כן, Vayomer tefateh vegam tuchal tzei
va'asei chen, seduce him and be successful, go and do this. Okay,
and then this spirit went and, you know, came to
צדקיהו בן כנענה Tzidkiyahu ben Kena'anah and gave him this prophecy. So
he thought it was a genuine prophecy from God, but it was
not, it was this false spirit. It was actually interesting, God even
allowed the false spirit to go. Okay, and the prophecy was "go
to war, you'll be successful" and in the end it was to
deceive him and he fell in battle. אמר
רב יהודה מאי צא,
Amar Rav
Yehuda mai tzei, what does צא tzei mean? צא ממחיצתי, Tzei mimchitzati,
leave my quarters, leave my domain, because which is
again maybe trying to deal with the idea that God is allowing
it to do, encouraging it to do, but it's not coming from
God, it's actually a false prophet. מאי רוח, Mai ruach, now what
was this רוח? ruach? אמר רבי יוחנן רוח של נבות היזרעאלי הוה.
Amar Rabbi Yochanan ruach shel Navot Hayizre'eli havah. So נבות היזרעאלי, Navot
Hayizre'eli, there was the spirit of נבות היזרעאלי Navot Hayizre'eli that אחאב
Achav had killed, and he was now using the opportunity to go
have אחאב Achav fall in battle, which God sort of had wanted
to happen. But it was a false prophet because the prophet was
telling אחאב Achav "you should go fight and you'll be successful". So
anyway, the Gemara says, okay, so צדקיהו Tzidkiyahu is giving this prophecy
and it wasn't from God, but how could you punish him? He
thought he was a genuine, honest, real prophet. So the Gemara says,
where was he? So the Gemara says no, הוה ליה למדע, havah
leih lemada, צדקיהו Tzidkiyahu should have paid attention, should have been careful,
כרבי יצחק, keRabbi Yitzchak, because he should have followed the teaching of
רבי יצחק, Rabbi Yitzchak, דאמר רבי יצחק סגנון אחד עולה לכמה נביאים,
deamar Rabbi Yitzchak signon echad oleh lekama nevi'im, one type of like
theme, one I mean it's like content, a vision
is given to many prophets, ואין שני נביאים מתנבאים בסגנון אחד, ve'ein
shenei nevi'im mitnabe'im besignon echad, but two prophets never exactly give the
same prophecy in the exact same language. So סגנון signon here, it's
like used different ways. In the first way, it sort of means
the content, like one idea can be given to multiple prophets, but
ואין שני נביאים מתנבאים בסגנון אחד, ve'ein shenei nevi'im mitnabe'im besignon echad,
that's like a common phrase which is: people say things, they articulate
the same idea in different ways. Okay, so nobody would have said
the exact same words. Each prophet, it goes sort of gets refracted
through the prophet's own, you know, lens and intellect and each one
gets expressed in a unique way. Okay, so where do you see
this?
עובדיה אמר זדון לבך השיאך, Ovadyah amar zedon libcha hishi'echa, עובדיה Ovadyah
said the, you know, brazenness of your heart or whatever, you know,
has misled you. ירמיהו אמר תפלצתך השיא אתך זדון לבך. Yirmeyahu amar
tiflatzecha hishia otcha zedon libcha. Okay, almost the same thing, זדון לבך
השיאך, zedon libcha hishi'echa, etc., but a slightly different phrasing. So you
should have known, and what was happening here was that all of
the prophets
who were telling, who were saying this, were saying the exact same
language. והני
מדקאמרי כולהו כהדדי, Vahani mideka'amri kulhu kachada, and in this case, since
all the prophets at this time were saying the exact same. the
exact same word שמע מינה לאו כלום קאמרי Shma mina lav klum
ka-amrei they should have realized that they were not really getting a
true prophecy because everybody was saying the exact same words. So the
גמרא Gemara for once challenges the what do you call it the
anachronism and says דילמא לא הוה ידע ליה להא דרבי יצחק dilma
lo hava yada lei le-ha d'Rabbi Yitzchak maybe they didn't know רבי
יצחק's Rabbi Yitzchak teaching. How were they supposed to know that when
everybody is saying the exact same thing it's not a true prophecy?
So the גמרא Gemara says יהושפט הוה התם. Yehoshaphat hava hatam. No,
יהושפט Yehoshaphat was there. וקאמר להו v'ka-amar le-hu and he was telling
them that what they were saying wasn't true prophecy. דכתיב ויאמר יהושפט.
d'chtiv vayomer Yehoshaphat. And יהושפט Yehoshaphat said, האין פה נביא לה' עוד?
ha'ein po navi l'Hashem od? Is there no other true נביא navi
true of God
here? So אמר ליה האיכא כולהו. amar lei heicha kulhani. So they
said, what do you mean? All these people, they're prophets of God,
why are you not accepting their prophecy? They're telling אחאב Achav to
go testify. So אמר ליה amar lei says כך מקובלני מבית אבי
אבא. kach mikubalni mibeis avi aba. This is the tradition I have
from my father's father's house. סגנון אחד עולה לכמה נביאים ואין שני
נביאים מתנבאים בסגנון אחד. signon echad oleh l'chama nevi'im v'ein shenei nevi'im
mitnab'im b'signon echad. Okay, so presumably since יהושפט Yehoshaphat was challenging them
and the גמרא Gemara is now reading in that he was telling
them you can't be receiving true prophecy because you would not be
saying
the same thing, they should have known and realized what they were
saying was not true prophecy. Now it still raises a question like
okay but is that going to make them מזיד meizid and חייב
מיתה? chayav misa? Like I believe that I really had this, because
I should really realize logically, my experience was some spirit came and
filled me and made me believe I had this prophecy to give
over. It's really unclear here in this גמרא. Gemara. But if I
should have known logically based on the rule it couldn't be true,
but I was still saying it, I should have realized that I
was saying over a prophecy that wasn't from God. That's what it
seems to be saying. Alright, anyway but that's an example of somebody
who says a prophecy not from God. The easier example is you
just סתם stam make it
up. המתנבא מה שלא נאמר לו hamisnabay ma shelo ne'emar lo something
that wasn't said to you but was said to somebody
else. כגון חנניה בן עזור kegon Chananya ben Azur דקאי ירמיה בשוקא
עילאה. d'ka'ei Yirmiyah beshuka ila'ah. חנניה בן עזור Chananya ben Azur that
ירמיה Yirmiyah was at the upper marketplace וקאמר כה אמר ה' צבאות
הנני שובר את קשת עילם. v'ka-amar ko amar Hashem tzeva'os hineni shover
es keshes Eilam. I will break
the bow of עילם, Eilam, which is one of the nations that
came together with בבל. Bavel. נשא חנניה קל וחומר בעצמו. nasa Chananya
kal v'chomer b'atzmo. So חנניה Chananya made a קל וחומר. kal v'chomer.
ומה עילם שלא בא אלא לעזור לבבל. uma Eilam shelo ba ela
la'azor l'Vavel. עילם Eilam that is coming only to help בבל Bavel
to destroy Israel אמר הקדוש ברוך הוא הנני שובר את קשת עילם.
amar Hakadosh Baruch Hu hineni shover es keshes Eilam. I'm going to
break their strength. כשדים עצמם Kasdim atzmam the כשדים Kasdim themselves על
אחת כמה וכמה. al achas kama v'kama. How much more so will
God visit punishment on them? ואתא איהו בשוקא תתאה ואמר. v'asa ihu
beshuka tata'ah v'amar.
And he said, כה אמר ה' שברתי את עול מלך בבל. ko
amar Hashem shavarti es ol melech Bavel. I will break the yoke
of בבל. Bavel. So there even though that was reasonable to think
that that's what God wished and would have said or whatever, he
did not receive that prophecy. So the גמרא Gemara says אמר ליה
רב פפא לאביי amar lei Rav Papa l'Abaye הא לחבירו נמי לא
נאמר. ha l'chaveiro nami lo ne'emar. That's not exactly the case. Because
we're talking about a case where you say something that you didn't
hear but your colleague heard. Here ירמיה Yirmiyah didn't hear that at
all. ירמיה Yirmiyah just heard about עילם. Eilam. So אמר ליה amar
lei כיון דאיתיהיב ליה קל וחומר למידרש keivan d'isyehiv lei kal v'chomer
l'midrash look
you're able to make a קל וחומר. kal v'chomer. Again I don't
know exactly about קל וחומר kal v'chomer at historical events and what's
going to happen in the future but okay. But since the קל
וחומר kal v'chomer is a legitimate one כמאן דאיתמר ליה דמי. keman
d'isamar lei dami.
So it's as if it was said to ירמיה Yirmiyah that God
will destroy not only עילם Eilam but also בבל. Bavel. That stands
completely totally reason. So I don't know and if ירמיה Yirmiyah would
have said God said בבל Bavel would be destroyed that would have
been okay. Not clear. But it sounds like it. But because he
now said it as if he had heard it,
that makes
it חנניה Chananya said it as if he had heard it that
makes him a נביא שקר navi sheker because it was not said
to him even if it was effectively said to ירמיה. Yirmiyah. הוא
ניהו דלא
נאמר לו. hu nihu d'lo ne'emar lo. It wasn't said to him.
המתנבא בשם עבודה זרה. hamisnabay b'shem avodah zarah. Now what's a case
of עבודה זרה? avodah zarah? כגון נביאי הבעל. kegon nevi'ei haBa'al. That's
easy, like the נביאים nevi'im of the בעל. Ba'al. Now again all
those sort of fall under the category of לא נאמר לו. lo
ne'emar lo. הכובש את נבואתו. hakovesh es nevu'aso.
Somebody who suppresses his נבואה. nevu'ah. כגון kegon last line here of
פ"ט עמוד א'. Peit Tes amud aleph. יונה בן אמיתי. Yonah ben
Amitai. יונה, Yonah, the prophet יונה Yonah who ran away rather than
to give his prophecy. So those so now we're moving into כובש
את נבואתו. kovesh es nevu'aso. So עבודה זרה avodah zarah and what
wasn't said to you that's חייב מיתה בידי אדם. chayav misa bidei
adam. Now now we're חייב מיתה בידי שמים. chayav misa bidei shamayim.
Suppressing your נבואה nevu'ah והמוותר על דברי נביא v'hamivater al divrei navi
somebody who violates what the נביא navi says. כגון kegon top of
פ"ט עמוד ב'. Peit Tes amud beis. For
example חברי דמיכה. chavrei d'Michah. The colleague of
מיכה. Michah. דכתיב
איש אחד מבני הנביאים d'chtiv ish echad mibnei hanevi'im אמר אל רעהו
בדבר ה' amar el re'ehu bidvar Hashem הכיני נא. hakeini na. So
one person said to his fellow smite me and we have a
tradition that this was מיכה. Michah. מיכה Micha was saying it and
he was doing this in order that he should look beaten up
and then he was going to go to אחאב Achav and use
it to give a message to אחאב. Achav. Okay, but so here
a נביא navi מיכה Micha said to this person, beat me up,
hit me, וימאן האיש להכותו, vaya'ma'en ha'ish lehakoto, and he refused even
though a נביא navi told him to do it. וכתיב, uchitiv, ויאמר
לו יען אשר לא שמעת, vayo'mer lo ya'an asher lo shamata, because
you did not listen, so blah blah blah, and then in the
end it says that a lion came out and ate him and
consumed him and he died. That was God, God, אנוכי אדרוש
מעמו, Anochi edrosh me'imo, he because he violated what the נביא navi
said. נביא שעבר על דברי עצמו, Navi she'avar al divrei atzmo, what's
a case of a נביא navi violating his own words? כגון עידו
הנביא, kegon Ido HaNavi, דכתיב כי כן צוה אותי, dichtiv ki chen
tziva oti, because by עידו הנביא Ido HaNavi he says, you know,
that he went and he said to this person, you know, God
has commanded me you should not eat bread and you should not
drink water. And this person says, ויאמר לו גם אני נביא כמוך,
vayo'mer lo gam ani navi kamocha, but what do you mean? I'm
a נביא navi like you, and I say it is okay to
eat and drink. וכתיב וישב אתו, uchitiv vayashov ito,
and this עידו הנביא, Ido HaNavi, even though he knew better from
God, he went ahead and he listened to this other person who
also claimed to be a נביא navi and he ate and he
drank. וכתיב וילך וימצאהו אריה, uchitiv vayelech vayimtza'ehu aryeh, another case of
another lion finding him and destroying him. So he violated his own
word and he was eaten by a lion as was the first
case of also this מיכה, Micha, this person who wouldn't hit מיכה,
Micha, and he was eaten by a lion. And you know
יונה Yona was swallowed by a whale, but eventually of course or
not a whale, excuse me, a fish, eventually got saved. Okay, תני
תנא קמיה דרב חסדא, tani tana kamei de'Rav Chisda, a תנא tana
learned in front of רב חסדא: Rav Chisda: הכובש נבואתו לוקה, hakovesh
nevu'ato lokei,
if somebody holds back his נבואה, nevuah, he gets מלקות, malkus, okay?
So because, you know, I first of all you have to get
the לאו lav of what exactly, but okay, but before you get
to pointing out what פסוק pasuk you're violating, he said a better
question. He said, אמר ליה מאן דאכל תמרי בארבילא לקי? amar lei
man de'achal tamrei be'arbila laki?
So according to you, if somebody if somebody were to eat dates
in a sieve, that's an ארבילא arbila is, would he get מלקות?
malkus? But that's the way רש"י Rashi explains it, but it's better
to read that this ארבילא arbila is just some like distant location,
like saying if somebody eats dates in the middle of a forest,
like would he get מלקות? malkus? Nobody would know about it. So
whatever
it was some idiom, but basically it means how can you give
testimony that this guy suppressed his נבואה? nevuah? How are somebody supposed
to know and to warn him? Besides the fact that it's a
he's not doing anything active, besides the fact we'd have to find
the לאו lav that he's over. Okay, fine. But anyway,
how could anybody even give him warning? So מאן מתרי ביה, man
matrei bei, who can warn him? אמר אביי חברי נביאי, amar Abayei
chavrei nevi'ei,
so his colleague נביאים, nevi'im, he they would know that he received
the נבואה. nevuah. מנא ידעי, mena yad'ei, how do they know? אמר
אביי דכתיב כי לא יעשה ה' אלוהים דבר כי אם גלה סודו,
amar Abayei dichtiv ki lo ya'aseh Hashem Elokim davar ki im galah
sodo, you know, God will never, you know, do something unless He
has revealed His secret to his to the
נביאים. nevi'im. So understand that to mean that like He wouldn't tell
one נביא navi something unless He told another נביא, navi, so somebody
else knows about this.
Okay, which is also still pretty interesting. It's sort of not publicly
available information,
you know, how you can sort of trust somebody to testify, I
knew through a נבואה nevuah this and therefore I warned him that
he had received it. All right. Anyway, ודילמא הדרי ביה, udilma hadrei
bei, maybe, you know, the God reversed Himself? And this is a
whole question, right, about how do you know like if a נביא
navi predicts something's going to happen and it doesn't happen because God
sometimes reverses Himself when people do תשובה? teshuva? So a whole complicated
issue. But anyway, maybe God reversed Himself? So maybe, you know, the
reason the נביא navi did not give this prophecy, assuming it was
a prophecy of doom or of punishment, was because God had retracted
it. No, אם איתא דהדרי ביה אודועי הוו מודעי לכולהו נביאי. im
ita de'hadrei bei odo'ei havu moda'ei lechulhu nevi'ei. No,
if it had been retracted, then all the נביאים nevi'im who knew
that it had been given would also know it had been retracted.
Okay. והא יונה דהדרי ביה ולא אודועוהו. veha Yona de'hadrei bei velo
odo'uhu. Wait
a minute, יונה Yona was, you know, it was retracted, but he
wasn't informed because it says that יונה Yona went outside to see
what was going to happen. So how so you see it could
be a prophecy could be given and retracted without the person being
informed, without the נביא navi being informed. הגמרא haGemara says no, מעיקרא
נינוה נהפכת אמרי ליה. me'ikara Ninveh nehepachet amrei lei.
Originally God said, מעיקרא נינוה נהפכת אמרי ליה. me'ikara Ninveh nehepachet amrei
lei. איהו לא ידע איהו לטובה איהו לרעה. ihu lo yada ihu
letova ihu lera'ah.
But יונה Yona didn't, you know, could have interpreted it either way.
יונה Yona didn't know: did it mean to turn over their deeds
and they'll do תשובה, teshuva, or it will be destroyed? So it
wasn't an actual retraction; now there was greater clarity into what that
original prophecy had actually meant. Anyway, fascinating idea that you could imagine
that you could give somebody התראה hatra'ah because you happen to know
the נבואה nevuah that that person received. Anyway, fascinating. But also fascinating
הגמרא's haGemara assumption that if one נביא navi knows something, other נביאים
nevi'im know something, and the idea also that sometimes נבואה, nevuah, you
know, prophecies are are retracted once people do תשובה. teshuva. All right,
so now הגמרא haGemara continues. המוותר על דברי נביא *Ha-mevater al divrei
navi*,
somebody now we're going to get to a really interesting question is
how do you know somebody is really a נביא *Navi* that you're
having an obligation to listen to them? Somebody who violates the words
of a נביא *Navi* gets punished by God, מיתה בידי שמים *Misa
biydei shamayim*. מנא ידע דעניש *Mena yada de-anish*, how do you know
that, how do you know that this guy's really a נביא *Navi*
that you should be punished for not listening to them? I mean,
look, we like had before, the guy said, "Hit me." You know,
I don't want to hit you. So how do you know the
guy's a נביא *Navi* that you're supposed to listen to him? דיהבי
ליה אות *Diyavlei os*, that he gives you a sign. So really
what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is saying is here, what proves, how
do you, you know, how do you prove that somebody is a
נביא *Navi* with the הלכה *Halachic* implications of then you have an
obligation to listen to him? So he gives you a sign, which
is what the
תורה *Torah* says,
ונתנה לך אות *Ve-nasna lach os*, right? So okay, והיכא דלא יהבי
ליה אות וענש *Ve-heicha dlo yahavei lei os ve-anash*,
but in the case of מיכה *Micha* where he said, "Hit me,"
you know, he didn't give him a sign to show this guy
that he was a true נביא *Navi*. היכא דמוחזק שאני *Heicha de-muchzak
shani*. Oh, if the guy is known to be a נביא *Navi*,
that's different. Then he doesn't have to give you a sign when
he tells you to do something. He's already established himself as a
נביא *Navi*. So what establishes somebody as a נביא *Navi*? So if
you look at רש״י *Rashi*, רש״י *Rashi* says, היכא דהוחזק דצדיק ונביא
אמת *Heicha de-huchzak de-tzaddik ve-Navi emes*, that he's righteous and a נביא
אמת *Navi emes*. How do you know that he's a נביא אמת
*Navi emes*? Because in the past, he's been saying things and they've
been coming true. Okay, now is that the same as a sign?
You know, is a sign something that's wondrous and that's not the
normal acts of nature? But if somebody says, you know, tomorrow this
stock's going to go up two points and it goes up two
points, is that, you know, like he predicts the future? Is that
constitute a sign or not? Not clear. But anyway, but רש״י *Rashi*
also says that, you know, you know he's a צדיק *Tzaddik* and
that's an interesting question. רמב״ם *Rambam* also deals with this. How much
is it about the person's character that's considered מוחזק *Muchzak* and how
much is it that the person has already done and prophesied things
that have come true and actually demonstrated that they're a נביא *Navi*,
maybe without what would technically be called a sign? All right, so
a lot of interesting questions open for interpretation here. דאי לא תימא
הכי *De-ee lo teima hachi*, because if you don't say that, אברהם
Avraham, בהר המוריה היכי שמיע ליה ליצחק *Avraham be-Har ha-Moriah heichi shamia
lei le-Yitzchak*? How did יצחק Yitzchak. *Yitzchak* listen to אברהם Avraham *Avraham*
and agree to allow himself get slaughtered? Now if you just think
about that, אברהם Avraham *Avraham* definitely gets the צדיק *Tzaddik* category, you
know? Does he get the אות *Os* category? Not exactly clear. I
mean, you know, when did אברהם Avraham *Avraham* ever give a sign?
You know, when did אברהם Avraham *Avraham* ever exactly prophesy about the
future? But you certainly knew that God was with אברהם Avraham *Avraham*.
I mean, so it raises really interesting questions. אליהו בהר הכרמל היכי
סמכי עליה ועבדי שחוטי חוץ *Eliyahu be-Har ha-Karmel heichi samchi alei ve-avdi
shechutei chutz*? How about אליהו *Eliyahu*? He told them to actually violate
an איסור דאורייתא *Issur d'Oraisa* and bring a קרבן *Korban* outside of
the בית המקדש *Beis ha-Mikdash* when he was showing up the נביאי
הבעל *Neveiei ha-Ba'al*. How did they listen to him? אלא היכא דמוחזק
שאני *Ela heicha de-muchzak shani*. If somebody is מוחזק *Muchzak* as a
נביא *Navi*, okay, as somebody who regularly is in communication with God,
you know, then that's different. But again, it sort of begs the
question, what establishes that? ויהי אחר הדברים achar hadevarim האלה *Vayehi achar
hadevarim ha-eileh*. Now since we mentioned the עקידה *Akeida*, now we're going
to digress a little and talk about the עקידה *Akeida*. ויהי אחר
הדברים האלה והאלהים נסה את אברהם Avraham *Vayehi achar hadevarim ha-eileh veha-Elokim
nisa es Avraham*. It was after these things God tested אברהם Avraham
*Avraham*. אמר רבי יוחנן משום רבי יוסי בן זמרא *Amar Rabbi Yochanan
mishum Rabbi Yossi ben Zimra*, what's after what things? אחר דבריו של
שטן Satan *Achar devarav shel Satan*. After the words of the שטן
Satan *Satan*. דכתיב *De-chsiv*, ויגדל הילד ויגמל ויעש אברהם Avraham, משתה גדול
ביום הגמל את יצחק et Yitzchak. *Vayigdal hayeled vayigamel vaya'as Avraham mishteh
gadol beyom higamel es Yitzchak*. He made a big feast. אמר שטן
Satan לפני הקדוש ברוך הוא *Amar Satan lifnei ha-Kadosh Baruch Hu*. The
שטן Satan. *Satan* said before הקדוש ברוך הוא *ha-Kadosh Baruch Hu*, רבונו
של עולם *Ribbono shel Olam*, זקן זה חננתו למאה שנה פרי בטן
*Zaken zeh chonantto le-meah shana peri beten*. This old man that you
after a hundred years have finally given him, you know, the fruit
of his womb, מכל סעודה שעשה לא היה לו תור אחד או
גוזל אחד להקריב לפניך *Mikol seuda she-asah lo hayah lo tor echad
o gozal echad lehakriv lefanecha*. From all the meals that he made,
he didn't have one like turtledove, you know, one one little bird
to offer for you as a קרבן *Korban*? Which is interesting. We
don't see that he did
that. So what's going on here? He's not showing proper gratitude. אמר
לו Amar lo *Amar lo*, God said to the שטן Satan *Satan*,
כלום עשה אלא בשביל בנו *Klum asah ela bishvil beno*. See, look,
he's doing this whole feast for the sake of his son. To
show you how much אברהם Avraham, *Avraham* values me, it's not a
question of would he offer up a little קרבן *Korban* for me,
but אילו אני אומר לו זבח את בנך et bincha לפני מיד
זובחו *Ilu ani omer lo zvach es bincha lefani miyad zovcho*. If
I even ask him for a son, if I even tell him
slaughter your son before me, and he's doing all this for his
son, if I even ask him for a son,
he would immediately agree to do it. מיד והאלהים נסה את אברהם
Avraham *Miyad veha-Elokim nisa es Avraham*. God tested אברהם Avraham *Avraham*. I'm
not going to get into the obvious theological issues here of who
is God trying to prove this to? רמב״ן *Ramban* says God doesn't
need to prove anything to God's self. This is only to prove
to to bring אברהם Avraham *Avraham's* potential out into, you know, to
actualize the potential that אברהם Avraham *Avraham* has. But the מדרש Midrash
*Midrash* here is making God showing up the שטן Satan *Satan*. ויאמר
קח נא את בנך. kach na et bincha. אמר רבי שמעון בן
אבא Amar Rabbi Shimon ben Abba אין נא אלא לשון בקשה. ein
na ella lashon bakasha. נא Na means please. משל למלך בשר ודם
שעמדו עליו מלחמות
הרבה. Mashal lemelech basar vadam she'amdu alav milchamot harbeh.
There was like a king that had a lot of wars. והיה
לו גיבור אחד vehaya lo gibbor echad and he had one major,
hero,
valorous soldier. וניצחן venitzchan and he was able to win all the
wars. לימים עמדה עליו מלחמה חזקה Leyamim amda alav milchama chazaka and
then there was like a extremely difficult war that came. אמר לו
בבקשה ממך Amar lo bevakasha mimcha and he said to his general
please, עמוד לי במלחמה זו amod li bemilchama zu I need, stand
up to me for this war. שלא יאמרו ראשונות אין בהם ממש
shelo yomru rishonot ein bahem mamash so people shouldn't say the easier
wars those were easy, that what the general was able to do,
but it doesn't prove anything he couldn't do the real difficult war.
אף הקדוש ברוך הוא אמר לאברהם Af hakadosh baruch hu amar leAvraham
God said to אברהם, Avraham ניסיתיך בכמה ניסיונות nisiticha bechama nisyonot
I have tested you with many tests. ועמדת בכולן ve'amadta bechullan you
succeeded in all them. עכשיו עמוד לי בניסיון זה Achshav amod li
benisayon zeh
but now please here's going to be the hardest one and I
need you to pass it. שלא יאמרו אין ממש בראשונים shelo yomru
ein mamash berishonim so people should not dismiss everything that you have
done prior to this. Okay, so that's קח נא kach na את
בנך
your son. שני בנים יש לי shnei banim yesh li this is
the famous רש"י, Rashi, quotes this. Your son. אברהם said back I
have two sons, ישמעאל ויצחק. Yishmael veYitzchak. את יחידך et yechidecha no,
your only son. זה יחיד לאמו וזה יחיד לאמו zeh yachid le'immo
vezeh yachid le'immo each one is unique to his mother. אשר אהבת
asher ahavta the one you love. תרווייהו רחמינא tavreihu rachmina
I love both of them. It's really beautiful because you see that
about how אברהם loves ישמעאל Yishmael and how difficult it is for
אברהם to send ישמעאל Yishmael out. Okay, so then it finally says
את יצחק. Yitzchak Fine, יצחק. Yitzchak, וכל כך למה Vechol kach lama
why did God build it up, why didn't he just say קח
את יצחק? kach et Yitzchak? וכל כך למה? Vechol kach lama? כדי
שלא תטרף דעתו עליו kedai shelo titaref da'ato alav
so in order that אברהם should not be overwhelmed by the shock,
this gives אברהם time to acclimate to what God is going to
ask him. קידם שטן
לדרך.
Kiddem Satan
laderech. Now the שטן Satan as אברהם started taking יצחק Yitzchak, to
הר מוריה Har Moriah the שטן Satan, sort of jumped in front
of him. אמר לו Amar lo and said to him, הנסה דבר
אליך תלאה. Hanesa davar elecha tileh. This is from איוב. Iyov. Will
he test you on a matter and you will grow weary? הנה
ייסרת רבים Hineh yisarta rabbim behold
you have warned many. וידיים רפות תחזק veyadayim rafot techazzek
and you have strengthened weak hands. כושל יקימון מילך koshel yekimun milecha
your words have lifted up those that would stumble. כי עתה תבוא
אליך ותלא ki atah tavo elecha vetila now it comes to you
and you weary? So this is what one of איוב'ס Iyov's colleagues
was saying to him. You have always been such a strong source
of faith for other people. Now that you've been challenged, how can
you let
yourself stumble? That was the פשט pshat of the פסוק. pasuk. But
the way the גמרא is reading it is the following, is that
he basically said to him, the way רש"י Rashi understands this, is
he said that והאלוהים ניסה את אברהם Vehaelohim nisa et Avraham could
God after you have been so strong and strengthened so many people,
הנסה hanesa like והאלוהים ניסה את אברהם, Vehaelohim nisa et Avraham, God
should test you with this thing and make you weary and give
you this
terrible test that demands so much from you, especially after everything you've
done for everyone else?
Okay. And as רש"י Rashi says, it will like destroy your children.
Okay.
So how could God do this thing to you? You know what
also is possible you could also say is that you have strengthened
everybody with the idea of belief in God and morality and so
on, and now by putting this on you, it's going to undermine
the way all the ethical teachings that you've been bringing to the
world. אמר לו Amar lo אברהם said back to him, אני בתומי
אלך Ani betumi elech I don't ask questions. God asks me, I'm
doing it. You're right, it doesn't make sense. Sort of like the
opposite of איוב, Iyov, rather than challenge, I will just accept and
do what God has asked me. אמר לו Amar lo so now
going back to the פסוק pasuk from איוב. Iyov. הלא יראתך כסלתך
Halo yiratcha kislatecha behold your fear is your
foolishness. You're saying that you're being ירא אלוהים yereh Elohim you're really
just being foolish. אמר לו Amar lo he said back to him,
זכור נא מי הוא נקי אבד Zechor na mi hu naki avad
know who is innocent that is
destroyed. Meaning, so I just have to accept whatever God's judgment is.
כיוון דחזא דלא קא שמע ליה Keivan dechaza dela ka shema leh
once the שטן saw that he was not being successful persuading אברהם,
אמר לו amar lo, and ואלי דבר יגונב ve'elai davar yigunav
I had this thing was like a stolen thing, this like I
got this secret message, said the שטן. כך שמעתי מאחורי הפרגוד Kach
shamati me'achorei hapargod this is what I heard from behind the curtain.
שה לעולה ואין יצחק לעולה seh le'olah ve'ein Yitzchak le'olah that God
isn't really even going to ask you for יצחק, Yitzchak, he's really
just going to ask you to bring a sheep. So maybe that
also he was saying that to undermine אברהם, because now אברהם would
do it just believing he wasn't really being asked to bring יצחק,
Yitzchak. and it would not be the same succeeding in the test.
So he was trying to sort of, you know, sort of ruin
the surprise but undermine the value of the test. And אברהם said
back to him, אמר לו, amar lo, כך עונשו של בדאי, kach
onsho shel badai, you know what he said? Like, maybe you're right,
but who knows, this is the punishment that the liar gets, אפילו
אמר אמת אין שומעים לו, afilu amar emet ein shomim lo, even
if you're telling the truth, nobody believes you anymore. I believe God
has asked me for יצחק, Yitzchak I'm going to listen to God,
I'm not going to listen to all the things that you are
saying. You know נחמה ליבוביץ, Nechama Leibowitz, by the way, has a
beautiful interpretation, and she says that the שטן in this case, in
this another similar מדרש Midrash where the שטן says, people are going
to call you a murderer, you know, how could God really be
asking you, that this is the מדרש sort of giving אברהם's own
inner turmoil and inner conflict and making it like externalizing it, and
that the שטן is representing the ways that אברהם himself is grappling
and struggling, which makes it much more powerful. I mean, if it
was not a test, if he wouldn't have had doubts and grappling,
right, would it have been a test at all is a question
that needs to be asked. Okay, let's just read a little bit
more. רבי אומר, Rabbi omer, it's not
אחר הדברים that means the word of the שטן, but אחר דבריו
של ישמעאל achar devarav shel Yishmael to יצחק. Yitzchak, אמר לו
ישמעאל
ליצחק, amar lo Yishmael l'Yitzchak, ישמעאל Yishmael said to יצחק Yitzchak, on
the day that, you know, they made this whole party for יצחק,
Yitzchak אני גדול ממך במצוות, ani gadol mimcha bemitzvot, that I am
better than you, שאתה מלת בן שמונה ימים, sheata malta ben shmoneh
yamim, maybe it wasn't on the day of the weaning, but whatever,
here this is what ישמעאל Yishmael said. You know, you got your
ברית מילה Bris Milah eight days old, ואני בן שלוש עשרה שנה,
v'ani ben shlosh esreh shanah, I was thirteen. אמר לו, ישמעאל Yishmael
said to him, ובאבר אחד אתה מגבה בי, uv'eiver echad ata megaveh
bi,
you're trying to show me how much, you know, better you are
than me because of one limb that you were willing to, you
know, undergo a difficult procedure for? אם אומר לי הקדוש ברוך הוא,
im omer li Hakadosh Baruch Hu, if God would have said to
me, זבח עצמך לפני, zevach atzmecha lifanai, offer yourself before me, אני
זובח, ani zoveach, I would agree to it. מיד והאלוקים ניסה את
אברהם. miyad v'HaElokim nisa et Avraham. Now what's nicer about this one
is that it gets יצחק, Yitzchak I mean, deals with the whole
problem: אברהם is being tested, יצחק Yitzchak is losing his life, where
is יצחק in this whole story? So here it brings in יצחק
as a subject as well. Okay, we will end with this for
now.